Finding Aid for Prohibition National Committee (U.S.) records, 1872-1972
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Prohibition National Committee (U.S.) records 1872-1972
Prohibition National Committee (U.S.)
86124 Bt 2
Minutes, 1888-1919, including; correspondence, newspaper clippings, and scrapbooks concerning party affairs; also papers, 1929-1970, concerning Prohibition Party in Michigan; papers, 1918-1930, concerning prohibition in Great Britain; papers, 1951-1958, concerning the National Temperance and Prohibition Council; and minutes, 1872, of the State Central Committee of the Prohibition Party of Michigan; also photographs and films.
8 linear feet
1 oversize folders
2 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was deposited by the party (donor no. 4545 ) and came through executive secretary Earl Dodge.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Prohibition Party constituted the partisan political element of the prohibition movement. Although the party achieved few victories at the ballot box, it provided an important forum for prohibition appeals and made the liquor issue a significant element in American politics for many years. The Prohibition National Committee was the governing body of the national Prohibition Party.
In 1869, top officials of the Independent Order of Good Templars, the Sons of Temperance and the Temple of Honor issued a call for a national convention to organize a Prohibition Party committed to securing and enforcing legislation to prohibit the production, distribution and sale of alcoholic beverages. On September 1, 1869, nearly 500 delegates representing nineteen states gathered at Farwell Hall, Chicago, where they organized the Prohibition Party, adopted a platform and elected as the first chairman of the Prohibition National Committee John Russell of Michigan. As leader of the first state-wide effort to organize a prohibition party, Russell had earned the recognition he later received as "Father of the Prohibition Party." Convinced that the liquor problem required political solutions, that success could only be secured through the party system, and that neither of the two major parties would ever give unqualified support to prohibition, the Prohibition Party's founders drew inspiration from the Republican Party's example of abolishing slavery by forming a new party based upon one dominant moral issue.
Like the Republican Party, the Prohibitionists recognized that they could never hope for electoral success by fastening themselves to a single issue. The Party's first presidential ticket and national platform, in 1872, were the first to advocate woman's suffrage, civil service reform, direct election of United States Senators, and prohibition. In 1896, the Prohibition Party endorsed a national income tax plan, making it the first political party to advocate each of the four issues which became amendments to the United States Constitution between 1872 and 1932. Party leaders boasted of their record as the vanguard of progressive political reforms. As a minority party, Prohibitionists sought support from many other political reform parties and societies. They fought not merely against saloons but also against the corrupt political parties and "debased politics" of the era. At various times resolutions of cooperation were considered or convention delegate representatives were exchanged with the Union Labor Party, the Populist Party the Socialist Labor Party, the Women's Party and the Universal Union War Extinction Prohibition Party. Yet the most important organization with which the Prohibition Party developed close relations was the Woman's Christian Temperance Union which, under the leadership of Frances E. Willard, from 1884 to 1898 exchanged delegates and gave ringing endorsements to the Prohibition Party. As vice-chairman of the Party for several years, Miss Willard strengthened the Party's stand in favor of woman's suffrage and its call for more education in public schools on alcohol problems.
The Prohibition Party never achieved significant success at the ballot box. From 1872 to 1932, the party's presidential candidates only twice, in 1888 and 1892, received more than 2% of the popular vote, and never gained more than 2.2%. Having received only 10,000 votes in its third presidential campaign in 1880, the Party was substantially reorganized to become by 1884 an aggressive, militant nation-wide political organization. In that year, former Republican governor of Kansas John P. St. John received over 150,000 votes on the Prohibition presidential ticket. He received more votes in New York than the margin of Grover Cleveland's close victory over James G. Blaine, thereby in effect denying the Republicans a national victory. Yet the Prohibition Party's national vote reached its peak of 270,000 in 1892, and never exceeded 1% of the vote after 1916. Although in certain states and in several local elections the party received consistent support and won occasional victories, the only candidates ever elected to national office on the Prohibition ticket were Kettel Halvorson of Minnesota, who won election to Congress in 1890, and Charles H. Randall of California, elected to Congress in 1914. Randall was re-elected twice, and served from 1915 to 1921 as a leading Congressional spokesman for prohibition. Although the Prohibition Party gained few election victories, it made prohibition an important political issue, exerting more influence over public opinion than the party's membership or votes would indicate.
The growth of the Populist and Socialist Parties, beginning in the 1890's, resulted in a decline of support for the Prohibition Party among those radical reformers whose commitment to prohibition was less strong than their interest in other social problems. Even among dedicated prohibition advocates, the party lost ground to the Anti-Saloon League, which was founded in 1893. The Anti-Salon League's "omni-partisan" policy supported and endorsed the most acceptable anti-liquor candidates for election, regardless of party, urging all temperance and prohibition voters to unite behind these candidates. The League explicitly rejected any alliance with the Prohibition Party, which they considered weak and ineffectual. Prohibitionists, in turn, denounced the Anti-Saloon League's willingness to compromise high principles in order to gain partial fulfillment of its goals and its support for local option laws, which blocked immediate progress toward state or national prohibition.
Ratification of the Eighteenth Amendment seemed, to many people, to many people, to mark the end of any need for the Prohibition Party, and some Party members even suggested disbanding the organization. Yet Prohibition Party leaders declared that only half of the battle had been won and that national prohibition could only be enforced and perpetuated when a party dedicated to these goals gained control of the government. At party conventions and National Committee meetings throughout the 1920's, Prohibitionists called for renewed efforts to gain final victory and adopted resolutions demanding that the major parties advocated and carry out strict enforcement of major victory and adopted resolutions demanding that the major parties advocated and carry out strict enforcement of prohibition laws. In defending the new legal status quo, the Prohibition Party moved farther and farther away from its earlier radical affiliations. In 1921, party leaders requested the government to deport any alien convicted of violating the Eighteenth Amendment and to deprive United States citizens similarly convicted of the right to vote. The 1924 Prohibition platform contained one plank proclaiming that the Bible should have a larger place in public schools and another declaring that unassimilated aliens were a menace to American institutions and should be Americanized. This was a far cry from the first Prohibition Party platform in 1872, which endorsed the Constitutional guarantees of civil and religious freedom and advocated the promotion of foreign immigration. The threat of prohibition repeal reinforced the party's backward-looking tendencies, making it for a number of years a conservative organization opposed to social change. Despite its greatly reduced influence and prestige, the Prohibition Party still continues to work for many of its original goals and to nominate candidates for office.
The Prohibition National Committee record group is arranged into the following series: Correspondence; Minutes and other papers; Press and printed; Sound recordings; Other organizations; and Visual materials. Except for the significant minute books of the party's national executive committee in the 1880s, most of the record group dates from the 20th century after the passage of the 18th Amendment. Information regarding the earliest years of the Prohibition Party in unfortunately missing in this record group.
Subjects:
Great Britain.; Michigan--Politics and government--1866-1876.; Michigan--Politics and government--1929-1938.; Michigan--Politics and government--1939-1945.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; National Temperance and Prohibition Council.; Presidents--United States--Election--1944.; Presidents--United States--Election--1948.; Presidents--United States--Election--1952.; Presidents--United States--Election--1956.; Presidents--United States--Election--1960.; Presidents--United States--Election--1964.; Presidents--United States--Election--1968.; Prohibition--United States.; Prohibition National Convention (1912: Atlantic City, N.J.); Prohibition National Convention (1916: Saint Paul, Minn.); Prohibition National Convention (1920: Lincoln, Neb.); Prohibition National Convention (1924: Columbus, Ohio); Prohibition National Convention (1928: Chicago, Ill.); Prohibition National Convention (1947: Winona Lake, Ind.); Prohibition National Convention (1951: Indianapolis, Ind.); Prohibition National Convention (1955: Milford); Prohibition National Convention (1959: Winona Lake, Ind.); Prohibition National Convention (1963: Saint Louis, Mo.); Prohibition National Convention (1967: Detroit, Mich.); Prohibition Party (Mich.); Prohibition National Committee (U.S.); Temperance--United States.; United States--Politics and government--20th century.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Babson, Roger Ward, 1875-1967.; Chafin, Eugene W. (Eugene Wilder), 1852-1920.; Churches.; Colvin, David Leigh, 1880-1959.; Decker, Rutherford L.; Dodge, Earl Farwell, 1932-; Exhibitions.; Families.; Hamblen, Stuart, 1908-1989; Hamblen family.; Holtwick, Enoch A., 1880?-1972.; Interiors.; Munn, Earle Harold, 1904-; Photography.; Political conventions.; Political elections--1940.; Political elections--1952.; Political elections--1956.; Political parades and rallies.; Prohibition--United States.; Prohibition Party (U.S.); Prohibition National Convention (1959: Winona Lake, Ind.); Slogans.; Temperance--United States.; Woman's Christian Temperance Union.; Watson, Claude A., 1885-
Contributors:
American Council on Alcohol Problems.; American Youth for Political Action.; Brown, Edmund G. (Edmund Gerald), 1905-1996.; Christian Amendment Movement.; Coate, Lowell H.; Collins, LeRoy.; Courtney, Kent.; Cox, James M. (James Middleton), 1870-1957.; Decker, Rutherford L.; Dodge, Earl Farwell, 1932-; Fisher, Rolland E.; Gibbons, Delmar D., 1913-; Hamblen, Stuart, 1908-1989; Hammaker, Wilbur Emery, 1876-1968.; Haydock, Earl Henry.; Hays, Will H. (Will Harrison), 1879-1954.; Hinshaw, Virgil G. (Virgil Goodman), 1876-1952.; Holdridge, Herbert C.; Hunt, H. L.; Kellogg, Frank B. (Frank Billings), 1856-1937.; Kohler, Julia B., d. 1969.; Levin, Sander, 1931-; MacArthur, Douglas, 1880-1964.; Morris, Sam.; Munn, Earle Harold, 1903-; Murphy, George, 1902-1992.; National Reform Association.; Ohio Council on Alcohol Problems.; Overholt, Gerald.; Shaw, Mark Revell, 1889-; Universal Union War Extinction Prohibition Party.; Wallace, George C. (George Corley), 1919-1998.; Watson, Claude A., 1885-; Woman's Christian Temperance Union.; Young, Coleman A.
Genre Terms:
Cartoons.; Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series dates from 1910 to 1972, with the bulk of material dating after 1950.
  - 1910-June 1967, 18 folders (Box 1)
  - July 1967-June 1971, 20 folders (Box 2)
  - July 1971-December 1972, 9 folders (Box 3)
- Minutes and other papers
  The Minutes and other papers series includes minutes of the proceedings of the Prohibition Party's national executive committee and national conventions in the period of 1888-1971. These records are continuous from 1888 to 1919.
  - Undated 1940-1972, 16 folders (Box 4)
  - Sarah Ulmer estate, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Minutes 1888-1919 of proceedings of National Executive Committee and of the National Convention, 2 volumes (Volume 1)
  - Minutes of National Committee and National Executive Committee
    - 1917-1928 (Box 4)
    - 1951-1971 (scattered issues) (Box 4)
  - Convention minutes and related
    - 1912-1928 (Box 4)
    - 1947-1955 (Box 4)
  - Convention addresses
    - 1916-1924 (Box 4)
    - 1940-1968 (Box 4)
  - Report of National chairmen and executive secretary 1949-1956 (Box 4)
  - State and regional materials
    - 1920-1925 (Box 4)
    - 1960-1972 (Box 4)
  - Campaign materials 1919-1924 (Box 4)
  - Financial materials
    - 1904-1927 (Box 4)
    - 1944-1960 (Box 4)
    - 1961-1970 (Box 4)
  - Contributions 1963-1965 (Box 4)
  - Receipt book
    - 1965-1968 (Box 4)
    - 1969-1972 (Box 4)
- Press and printed
  The Press and printed series consists of newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, press releases, newsletters and miscellaneous printed material.
  - Newspaper clippings
    - Undated (Box 5)
    - 1924 (Box 5)
    - 1925-1950 (Box 5)
    - 1951-1959 (Box 5)
    - 1960-1966 (Box 5)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 5)
    - 1969-1971 (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook
    - 1901-1920 undated (Box 5)
    - 1933 (Box 5)
  - Press releases 1963-1967 (Box 5)
  - Printed material 1908-1972, 2 portfolios (Box 5)
  - Printed material 1960s, 1 portfolios (Box 6)
  - Prohibition songs 1944-1949 (Box 6)
  - State and regional prohibition newsletters (Box 6)
- Sound recordings
  - Addresses of Rutherford L. Decker, E.A. Holtwick, Wilbur Hammaker, Rollin M. Severance, E. Harold Munn, Virgil Brock, and Earl Dodge, 13 audiotapes 5" and 7" reel-to-reel (Box 6)
- Other organizations
  The Other organizations series includes materials pertaining to the National Temperance and Prohibition Council and the Prohibition Party of Michigan. Included are minutes, 1872 and 1933-1934, of the Michigan State Central Committee.
  - E. Scrymgeour and the British Prohibition Party 1918-1930 (Box 7)
  - National Temperance and Prohibition Council
    - 1951-1958 (Box 7)
    - 1963-1967 (Box 7)
    - 1968-1972 (Box 7)
  - Prohibition Party of Michigan
    - Minutes
      - 1872 of the State Central Committee (Box 7)
      - 1933-1934 1961 (Box 7)
    - Minute book 1933-1942 including minutes, 1947-1953 of Kalamazoo County Prohibition Committee (Box 7)
    - Correspondence
      - 1933 (Box 7)
      - 1934 (Box 7)
      - 1936-1944 (Box 7)
    - Printed material
      - 1929-1933 (Box 7)
      - 1934-1944 (Box 7)
    - Papers
      - Undated (Box 7)
      - 1934 (Box 7)
      - 1935 (Box 7)
      - 1936-1940 (Box 7)
      - 1941-1943 (Box 7)
      - 1944 (Box 7)
      - 1945-1950 (Box 7)
      - 1951-1966 (Box 7)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual materials series includes both photographs and motion pictures. The photographs are of the Party's presidential candidates, other individuals, and party activities; There also some editorial cartoons. The films are of party conventions.
  - Photographs
    - Prohibition Party presidential candidates and campaigns
      - Babson, Roger W. (1940) (Box 7)
      - Chafin, Eugene W. (1908 and 1912) (Box 7)
      - Colvin, D. Leigh (1936) (Box 7)
      - Decker, Rutherford L. (1960) (Box 7)
      - Dodge, Earl F. (1984) (Box 7)
        (the photos are all earlier than 1984)
      - Hamblen, Stuart (1952) (Box 7)
      - Holtwick, Enoch A. (1956) (Box 7)
      - Munn, Earl H., Sr. (1964 1968, and 1972) (Box 7)
      - Watson, Claude A. (1944 and 1948) (Box 7)
    - Activities (Box 7)
    - Editorial cartoons (Box 7)
      (see also oversize folder Bt Out)
    - Individuals, Identified (Box 7)
    - Individuals, Unidentified (Box 7)
    - National convention, Winona Lake, Indiana (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
    - Negatives (Box 7)
      (staff use only)
  - Motion pictures
    - 1956 Convention: Enoch A. Holtwick acceptance speech, ca. 30 minutes (Box 8)
    - 1963 Convention, 3 film reels various times, ca. 15-30 min. (Box 8)
    - "The Brain is the Reason," 1958 Presented by the National Women's Christian Temperance Union; produced by Chicago Film Laboratories; revised by Charles Cahill and Associates., ca. 25 min. (Box 8)
      (This is a reedited version of "It's the Brain that Counts")
    - "Cancer by the Carton," 1958 Presented by the American Temperance Society; produced by Leston O. Post, ca. 30 min., color (Box 8)
    - "Skid Row," (documentary of Skid Row Chicago) circa 1950 Produced by Fred S. Niemann., ca. 25 min. (Box 8)
Selective Index to Correspondents
American Council on Alcohol Problems.
1967-1968
American Youth for Political Action.
1951
Brown, Edmund G. (Edmund Gerald), 1905-1996.
March 23, 1964
Christian Amendment Movement.
July, Aug., Sept., 1963
Coate, Lowell H.
Apr. 14, 1953, 1954
Collins, LeRoy.
Sept. 26, 1963
Courtney, Kent.
Dec. 28, 1960, Apr. 11, 1967
Cox, James M. (James Middleton), 1870-1957.
Sept. 5, 1920
Decker, Rutherford L.
June 30, 1947, July 8, 1947
Dodge, Earl Farwell, 1932-
1958, 1959, 1960, 1961, 1963, 1967, 1968
Fisher, Rolland E.
1968
Gibbons, Delmar D., 1913-
1958, 1959, 1960, 1961, 1963, 1964, 1965, 1966, 1967
Hamblen, Stuart, 1908-
Nov. 20, 1951
Hammaker, Wilbur Emery, 1876-1968.
Nov. 19, 1958, Jan., 31, 1968, May 20, 1968, May 28, 1968
Haydock, Earl Henry.
1968
Hays, Will H. (Will Harrison), 1879-1954
1920? Sept. 3, 1920, July 22, 1920
Hinshaw, Virgil G. (Virgil Goodman), 1876-1952.
Mar. 21, 1923, (1920?), July 22, 1920, July 17, 1916
Holdridge, Herbert C.
Nov. 20, 1954, Dec. 15, 1954, Jan. 13, 1955, Jan. 20, 1955
Hunt, H. L.
Apr. 11, 1967
Kellogg, Frank B. (Frank Billings), 1856-1937.
Dec. 2, 1925
Kohler, Julia B., d. 1969.
Aug. 6, 1965, 1967, 1968
Levin, Sander, 1931-
Mar. 15, 1965
MacArthur, Douglas, 1880-1964.
Oct. 11, 1951
Morris, Sam.
Oct. 1, 1964
Munn, Earle Harold, 1903-
Nov. 19, 1958, Nov. 20, 1958, 1963, 1964, 1967, 1966, 1968
Murphy, George, 1902-1992.
Oct. 23, 1966
National Reform Association.
May 29, 1963
Ohio Council on Alcohol Problems.
Feb. 3, 1966
Overholt, Gerald.
1951, 1952, 1953
Shaw, Mark Revell, 1889-
1967, Sept., 1968 (Sept. 20)
Universal Union War Extinction Prohibition Party.
July 20, 1916
Wallace, George C. (George Corley), 1919-1998.
Apr. 11, 1967, July 22, 1968
Watson, Claude A., 1885-
June 30, 1947, July 8, 1947, July 8, 1955, Oct- 12, 1964, Oct. 2, 1967
Woman's Christian Temperance Union.
Correspondence throughout
Young, Coleman A.
Mar. 22, 1965